本字幕由 YYeTs人人影视 原创翻译制作
仅供学习 禁止用于任何商业盈利行为
更多影视更新 请登陆 www.YYeTs.com
■
翻译   阿拉蕾
Translator  Analeigh
翻译  坏蛋小泡
Translator   Kingel
翻译     紫杉
Translator  Zishan_Stone
翻译   奥特慢
Translator  Ultrabear
时间轴   贝壳
Timer      JimmyBeck
时间轴  大米饭
Timer        Liko
校对  半糖
Editor   Angelia
后期  鱼骨头
Encoder   Fishbone
总监  猫家小丢
Leader    Adam.Diu
特别感谢  小石头
Special Thanks   Sienna
人类星球
第八集
只有一种生物为了自己的生存
Only one creature has carved
在地球的每一个角落都留下了印迹
a life for itself in every habitat on Earth.
那就是人类
That creature is us.
天地悠悠
All over the world, we still
我们仍依靠创造力来努力存活于世
use our ingenuity to survive in the wild places,
远离文明开化的城市
far from the city lights,
直面原始险恶的自然
face to face with raw nature.
苍茫大地之上
In all the wild places on earth,
挑战不断袭来  人类则越挫越勇
we have risen to the challenges nature has thrown at us.
怡然之居已然拔地而起
Now we have created the habitat of our dreams.
由己所建  为己所用
Designed by us, for us.
这达到了人类想象力和创造力的顶峰
The pinnacle of human imagination and ingenuity.
这一切让我们认为  人类就是地球的主宰
This is where we humans like to think we reign supreme,
驱逐不喜之物
driving out the nature we don't want...
真恶心
Oh, God!
运输所需之物
...shipping in what we do.
但是  自然不易掌控
But the natural world isn't easy to control.
人类能否真正在都市丛林中掌控自然
Can we humans ever really master nature in the urban jungle?
况且  这一做法明智吗
And is it wise to try?
城市
都市丛林求生记
迪拜是极度现代化的城市
Dubai is the ultimate modern city,
井然有序  熠熠发光  纤尘不染
orderly, sparkling and squeaky clean.
这是人类智慧的结晶
It's a temple to man's ingenuity,
是冉冉升起的沙漠之星
rising from the desert.
但是这里存在高空威胁
But there's a menace in the air.
鸽子
Pigeons.
无数只鸽子给这座清新的城市带来污秽
Thousands of them are making a mess in this pristine metropolis,
因此迪拜人不喜欢鸽子
and Dubai doesn't like it.
有个人能够提供帮助
One man can help.
阿拉伯人称他为阿尔赫
The Arabs call him Al Hurr.
他的名字叫大卫・斯塔德
His name is David Stead.
好孩子
Good lad.
他用猎鹰将鸽群赶出迪拜
His challenge is to keep Dubai pigeon free using falcons
用一种古阿拉伯方法解决现代都市问题
an ancient Arabian solution for a modern urban problem.
食肉鸟肯定会以鸟类为食
Birds of prey, of course, are hunting birds.
而猎鹰则是食肉鸟家族的一员
And the falcons, in the bird of prey family,
还是其中的高手
are the specialist bird-hunters.
它们靠捕食其他鸟类为生
They only catch other birds for a living.
所以  和其他食肉鸟相比
And, as a result, the pigeons are most scared of falcons,
猎鹰是鸽子最大的天敌
compared to any of the other birds of prey.
哪怕从未见过猎鹰的鸽子
So, even a pigeon that has never seen a falcon in its life
对类似猎鹰的轮廓外形
does have this almost genetic fear of the silhouette-
也有着天生的恐惧感
the shape- of a falcon.
今天  他和猎鹰尼墨一起
Today, he is working for some of Dubai's top hotels
为迪拜的顶级酒店驱赶鸽子
with his peregrine falcon Nimr.
尼墨现在有三岁了
Nimr is a three-year-old falcon now.
猎鹰一岁便已成年
They become adult at one.
她现在已经是相当成熟的猎鹰了
So she's now quite a mature falcon
尽管三岁  她还是有很多东西要学
although, at three, she still has an awful lot to learn.
整个猎鹰群中  她可能是最自负的一只
Out of the whole team, she's probably the most arrogant.
她有着强烈的野心
She has this tremendous attitude about her
知道谁在掌控一切
and she knows who's in charge.
我发誓  绝不是我们在掌控
And, I can assure you, it's not us.
城里的鸽子大肆毁坏着这些建筑
City pigeons damage these buildings.
它们的排泄物具有腐蚀性
Their corrosive droppings
会侵蚀铬合金和石材
erode chrome and stone,
每只鸽子每年产生十二公斤的排泄物
and each bird can produce 12 kilos of mess a year.
大卫并不是要杀死或捉住它们
But David's aim isn't to kill or even catch them.
他只希望将它们吓走
He is hoping to scare them away.
尼墨喜欢追逐游戏
And Nimr loves the chase.
但她毕竟是一只猎鹰
After all, she's a peregrine -
广袤天界中速度最快的生物
the fastest creature in the sky,
时速可达二百八十公里
capable of swooping at 280 kilometres an hour.
所以一旦她将鸽子赶走  大卫便将她唤回
So, once she's moved them on, he needs to tempt her back.
这是需要技巧的
And that's tricky.
她是只好奇心极强的猎鹰
She's an extremely inquisitive falcon,
这让我很崩溃
which can be frustrating for me,
因为当她飞走并看到有趣事物的时候
because I tend to lose all contact and control with her
很有可能会与我失去联系并失控
when she's flying and she sees something amusing.
但是总有一个赢得猎鹰芳心的方法
But there's always one way to a falcon's heart
那就是奖励她一顿鸡肉大餐
the promise of a chicken dinner.
由于大卫和尼墨的帮助
Thanks to David and Nimr,
迪拜的酒店远离了鸽子的困扰
Dubai's hotels remain pigeon free.
毕竟  没人想让鸽子粪毁了百万美元的美景
After all, no-one wants pigeon poo to spoil their million-dollar view.
有时候  将不受欢迎的野生动物赶出城
Sometimes, driving unwanted wildlife out of a town
需要更加现代的手段
requires a much more modern solution.
疯狂的麋鹿  精美野外家装饰品
斯坦・舒马克警官外出执勤
Sergeant Stan Schumaker is on a mission.
他就职于科罗拉多州的埃斯蒂斯公园
He works in Estes Park, Colorado.
每天他都开着一辆特殊警车外出巡逻
Every day he patrols his patch on an unusual police vehicle
一辆赛格威电动滑板车
a Segway scooter.
埃尔克霍恩大街
他的工作是保证街道畅通
His job is to keep the streets free of trouble.
此地区的麻烦很大且难以攻克
And trouble here is particularly large and spiky.
一旦麋鹿进入马路  整个城镇就一片混乱
Once the elk come in, getting around town's a hassle,
尤其是六月到十月初
pretty much from June to the beginning of October.
每年夏天  麋鹿都会侵扰这里
Every summer, the town is invaded by elk stags.
舒马克警官的工作就是确保当地居民的
Sergeant Schumaker's job is to make sure that the locals
日常生活不受影响
can go about their daily business.
一年中的这个时候可不好过
Not easy at this time of year.
麋鹿看起来很温顺
They may look placid,
但它们重达三百多公斤  高达三米
but elk weigh over 300 kilos, can be three metres tall
再加上有致命危险的鹿角
and their antlers are lethal.
城里到处可见它们的身影
They're pretty much everywhere in town.
整个山谷满是麋鹿
This whole valley is pretty much full of elk.
任一时间地点  数量都有五百到一千五
At any given time, there could be anywhere from 500 to 1,500.
雌性麋鹿对城市绿地偏爱有加
The female elk love the urban grasslands.
它们终年生活于此
They live here year round.
我们有两个大型高尔夫球场
We've got two main golf courses.
这里的草地是为打高尔夫球准备的
The grass is, of course, golf grass,
它们显然偏爱于此
so they absolutely love that.
雄性麋鹿们只是来逛逛
The male elk are only visiting.
并不是为了看高尔夫球赛
And it's not for golf.
它们回到城里就为了一件事
The boys are back in town for one thing
"求偶大对决"
a stag party.
每年这个时候
At this time of year,
雄鹿为争夺雌性进行决斗  这很危险
the stags fight over the females and can be very dangerous.
但是制造麻烦的还不仅仅是麋鹿们
But it's not just the elk causing problems.
舒马克警官还要疏散游客
Sergeant Schumaker also has to control the tourists.
绝大部分游客不知道这些动物是野生的
A lot of these tourists have no idea that these animals are wild.
这很荒唐  但是他们的确
It's the craziest thing, but they
认为这些动物已被驯化
for some reason they think these animals are tame.
游客中心
通行信息
没有比让一头发怒的麋鹿追逐更糟糕的了
There's no messing with an irritable elk.
危险
请勿靠近野生动物
回来
Get back, guys.
在二十一世纪的西部荒原
In the Wild West of the 21st century,
警官骑的白头大马换成了大型滑板车
the sheriffs white stallion has been replaced by a giant scooter.
麋鹿不喜欢赛格威车  我也不知道原因
The elk do not like the Segway. I don't know what it is.
我想是因为车的移动很特别
I think it's the movement,
因为这不是像正常人走路那样移动
because I'm not moving normal, as a human would walk.
开着赛格威车我会移动得很快
And I'm scurrying around a lot quicker on that Segway.
所以麋鹿不喜欢
So the elk do not like it whatsoever.
舒马克警官今天执勤很顺利
Today's been a good day for Sergeant Schumaker.
他把这个城镇的捣乱者都赶走了
He's run the troublemakers out of town.
但并不是所有的城市入侵者
But not all the invaders who
都这么容易被驱赶
come to our cities are so easy to chase away.
有些城市被一些狡黠
Some cities are plagued by creatures
和有生存技巧的生物所折磨
who are just as wily and streetwise as us.
斋浦尔  印度发展最快的城市之一
Jaipur, one of the fastest growing cities in India.
在这里  抢劫和小偷小摸屡见不鲜
Here, muggings and petty theft are part of everyday life.
夏康塔是当地集市的一个小贩
Shakuntla, a local market seller,
遭到街头暴徒的恐吓
is terrorised by street gangs.
但这些暴徒并不是当地的混混
And these are not the local lads.
它们不怕任何人
非常好斗  我们都怕它们
她每天都要面对它们
She has to face them every day.
那是一群可怕的动物
They're a terrifying bunch.
一小群恒河猴在屋顶上走来走去
A posse of rhesus macaques hang out on the rooftops.
若被它们的尖齿咬伤  后果非常严重
One bite from these canines can inflict horrible damage.
有一次  猴子们袭击一名妇女
最后只能去医院处理伤口
不知道她是否还活着
对于恒河猴来说  都市丛林里的生活甚至比
For the macaques, life in the urban jungle is even easier
在真正丛林里还要安逸
than life in the real one.
像我们一样  它们既聪明又老练
Like us, they can be smart and slick.
斋浦尔的寺庙和街道
Jaipur's temples and streets
为它们提供了偷窃的温床
provide endless pockets to pick.
而它们最爱的地方还是食品市场
And their favourite place is the food market.
今天  夏康塔的货摊
The question today is, will Shakuntla's stall
能否免遭猴子们的毒手呢
survive all the monkey business?
这次攻击由帮派老大率领  一只体壮的公猴
The attack is led by the gang leader, an alpha male.
恒河猴们的作战都是团队协作
The macaques work as a co-ordinated team,
声东击西
ducking and diving.
从多方位进行偷袭
Attacking from all angles,
小恒河猴分散夏康塔的注意力
the smaller macaques distract Shakuntla,
胆大的公猴大肆抢夺
while the bolder males grab the loot.
斋浦尔街道的生活可谓艰辛
Life on Jaipur's streets is tough enough.
但是当你的对手被神灵护佑时
But when your enemy is protected by a deity,
那就无计可施了
there's nothing you can do.
这些猴子是猴神哈努曼的化身
These monkeys are sacred to the monkey god Hanuman.
哈努曼是我们的神
而这些猴子是他的化身
是他授意它们来吃喝的
而我只能空手而归
猴子成为了集市上的一大威胁
Monkeys can be a menace in the market.
城市大道之下正在进行着大规模战役
But there is a wider war going on under all our city streets.
有些物种已经开始威胁
Some species have become a threat to our domination
人类对都市丛林的统治地位
of our very own urban world.
杰夫和朱尼尔正在巡街
Jeff and Junior are on a stakeout,
在曼哈顿的街头追捕人类的死敌
hunting down mortal enemies on the Manhattan front line.
我是纽约市的夜间灭虫专员
My job is a night-time exterminator in New York City.
上白班的同事们灭臭虫
Day-time guys where I work do bedbugs.
我们负责消灭餐馆里的老鼠和蟑螂
We just do rats, mice, roaches in restaurants.
你猜我们每天几点到这儿
What sort of time do you think we'll be getting up in this place?
不知道  据说是在午夜
I don't know. They said about midnight.
这里还没打烊
They're not closed yet.
我觉得告诉人们我的工作没什么问题
I mean, I don't really have a problem telling people what I do,
但是我们要尽力做到小心谨慎
but we try to be as discreet as possible,
就是因为不想让人们
just because I don't want people
以为他们在满是老鼠的地方吃饭
to think that they're eating in an area that's full of rats.
但是东村的老鼠很多  无法隐瞒身份
But East Village is full of them, so you can't hide that.
老鼠们也爱高级餐厅
Rats love fine dining too.
但是它们从不付小费
But they don't leave tips behind.
它们只会留下粪便和疾病
They leave excrement and disease.
没有人愿意承认纽约市面临着巨大的鼠患
No-one wants to admit that the Big Apple has a big rat problem,
所以杰夫和朱尼尔才要在夜晚工作
so Jeff and Junior only work at night.
垃圾是问题的源头
Trash is a big deal.
不讲卫生的人把垃圾扔在路边
Us being sloppy humans throwing trash out on the sidewalks,
喝剩的果汁
and leaving the juices and
肉汤  鸡骨头满地都是
meat juices and chicken bones everywhere.
知道吗  那对它们来说可是顿大餐
That's a buffet for them, you know what I mean?
今晚  他们将在唐人街安置捕鼠器
Tonight, they're laying traps in Chinatown.
你没事吧
Are you OK?
又有一只  伙计
Another one of these, man.
又是一只
Another one of these.
你是如何令你的餐馆变成这个样子的
How do you even leave your restaurant like this?
老天啊  伙计  过来瞧瞧
Oh, man! Dude, look at this.
看看这些东西  寿司  米饭  面条
Look at all of this stuff! Sushi, rice, noodles.
老鼠什么都吃
Rats will eat anything,
从杂碎到筷子  来者不拒
from chop suey to the chopsticks themselves.
我们有钥匙  所以能够在夜晚进来
We walk in at night because we have keys.
顾客离开后我们才能工作
We have to go when the customers are gone.
当食客们离开餐馆时
And when the people leave the restaurant,
老鼠们觉得是时候出来活动了
the rats think it's time to come out.
我们还要再过会儿进来
But we go in there later,
大概餐馆关门一小时后
like an hour after they close,
那时它们都出来狂欢了
so they're out partying.
看到它了
Uh-oh. There he is, there he is,
就在那里
there he is. Right there, right there.
就在那个地方
Right there, right there, right there, right there.
看见了吗
See him?
它向下爬走了
He's going down, he's going down.
就在那里  在那个洞里
Right there. Right in the hole.
该死
Damn!
-它应该是在喝咖啡  -也许
- He was drinking coffee. - Something.
这种家伙最需要的就是咖啡了
That's the last thing that this guy needs is coffee.
真是难以置信
Unbelievable!
所以我从来不吃外卖
That's why I don't eat takeout, man.
是啊  你不吃才怪
Yes, you do.
来  伙计  到地下室去看看
Come on. Let's go to the basement, man.
小心  这里很滑
Watch out, man. It's slippery.
地下室里还有另一种令人发麻的东西
And there's another horror in the basement.
看看天花板上的虫子
Look at the bugs in the ceiling!
你肯定没见过这么壮观的景象
You don't ever see that.
就在门后面
Right there behind the door.
蟑螂
Cockroaches.
这是专业灭蟑螂的技术
This is professional extermination.
我来处理这些虫子
I got these bugs.
你以前来过这间地下室吗
Oh! Have you seen this basement?
里面有什么  伙计
What's in there, man?
老式房屋通过管道和地下室互相连接
Old buildings connected by pipes and basements
使得老鼠和蟑螂在
allow the rats and roaches
城市里看不见的地方四处流窜
to scuttle through the city unseen.
这里太恶心了
It's disgusting in here.
水流得到处都是
Look at the water dripping all over the place.
一般我们尽量保持安静
We're basically trying to be quiet
仔细听任何类似
to hear noises for any, you know,
老鼠活动咬啮的声音
any signs of rat activities.
你听见了吗
You hear that? You hear that?
轻微的劈啪声
The little pitter-patter?
像指甲轻刮的声音
Little fingernails?
是的  在那里
Yup. Over here.
看这儿  可以直接看到...
Look at that. That goes right into the...
我能看到厨房
I can see the kitchen!
对于杰夫与朱尼尔来说  这是场长久战
For Jeff and Junior it's a lifelong fight.
据说在纽约
It's said there's at least one rat
有多少人就有多少只老鼠
for every person in New York.
那就是将近九百万只
That's nearly nine million rats.
就目前来看  人类战胜老鼠
As far as humans winning the battle over rats
应该是遥遥无期
nowhere close.
我不知道有什么办法能消灭它们
I don't even know how you would stop it,
真不知道
I really don't.
他们将利用一切可能的
They are going to use every contraption
奇特装备
they can devise
来对付可恶的害虫们
in the battle with the pests.
这是一个...
Well, this is a...
我并不想把它们都引出来  但是...
I don't want to call them out, but...
听听这个
Listen to that.
没有亲自来过的人们
All those people out there,
肯定无法想象这里发生了什么
they have no idea what's happening down here.
他们明天依旧会来这里就餐
And they're going to come eat here tomorrow.
这里可是全天半价啊
50% off all day, huh?
没错  难怪这么多人来
Yeah... Yeah, no wonder.
二十四小时之后
24 hours later,
杰夫和朱尼尔回来清点战果
Jeff and Junior are back to assess the death toll.
你好伙计
Ah, dude.
老鼠夹非常奏效
The snap traps have worked.
它还挺可爱的
He's cute.
这块捕鼠胶也战果颇丰
And the glue mats.
这只老鼠已经腐烂了
This one is decomposing.
还有老鼠药
And the poison.
老兄
Oh, dude!
-看看它的块头  -已经死了
- Look at the size of him! - He's dead.
看上去它当时奋力拼搏了一番
Looks like he's been fighting with something, bro.
看看它的牙齿
Damn! Look at them teeth, bro.
你说它得有多重
What's the weight on that?
我的手臂都酸了
I'm telling you, man. My arm got tired.
这只可真够厉害的
That's pretty... That's brutal.
真够大的
Oh, man!
这只是人类和死敌之间
This is just another night
永无休止的战争中的一夜而已
in the ongoing battle with our eternal enemies.
有时候我们要把它们装进袋子带走
Sometimes we'll walk out with bags of dead things
我一般用饭店提供的外卖袋
and I'll take a takeout bag from the restaurant
这样人们就以为我是来买外卖的
so people would think I'm leaving with takeout food.
还有更糟糕的
And it gets worse.
有些更小的生物会利用
There are other tiny creatures which take advantage
密集的都市人口而生存
of dense urban populations.
它们反而与我们亲密接触并加以利用
They exploit us in much more intimate ways.
大行其道  作威作福
They're reaching epidemic proportions.
不同于老鼠依赖我们为生
Not just feeding off us like rats,
它们简直就是以我们为食
but literally feeding on us.
家住伦敦的卡萝尔・安德森
Londoner Carol Anderson
就迎来了这些不速之客
has these unwanted house guests.
现在还有咬痕吗
Have you got any bites on you at the moment?
是这些吗
You mean these?
是的  就是被叮咬的这些伤痕
Yeah, the bites that you had all round here.
还是有些小红点吧
There's still little red marks from them, aren't there?
你觉得它们会藏在你房间的哪个地方
Where do you think they are in your room?
在床下吧
Down the side of the bed.
我也是这么想的
That's what I meant.
还在墙上爬来爬去
And crawling up the walls.
这种恼人的食客只在夜晚活动
Irritating parasites which only come out at night.
很好  过来
Right. Right. Come on, then.
该你了  上去吧
In you go. Hop up.
很好
That's it, then.
晚安  睡个好觉  别让...
Good night, sleep tight, don't let the...
臭虫咬到
Bedbugs bite.
但愿如此
Let's hope not.
臭虫就像是昆虫里的吸血鬼
Bedbugs are insect vampires
被二氧化碳
attracted to carbon dioxide,
热量还有人类的气味吸引而来
heat and body odours.
它们喜欢干净温暖的房子
They like clean, warm houses.
它们只吸食人类的血液
Their only food is human blood.
臭虫的数量真是令人生畏
The sheer numbers is quite daunting, really.
它们吸饱了血就顺墙而爬
They literally were streaming up the wall,
一直爬到天花板上
up to the ceiling, just full of blood.
每一只都喂得饱饱的
So they'd obviously all just been feeding.
每天早上醒过来第一件事
First thing in the morning,
就是检查身上被叮咬的痕迹
I woke up and looked up.
太恐怖了  恐怖之极
It was horrible, it really was horrible.
卡萝尔请来了
Carol calls in
业内最好的臭虫探测员
the best bedbug detector in the business,
一只叫查理的巧克力色的拉布拉多犬
Charlie the chocolate Labrador,
以及它的得力助手  驯犬师亚当
ably assisted by his handler, Adam.
沙发应该是
Right. Well, the sofa seems to
被污染最严重的  有很多臭虫在里面
be the worst affected. Got lots of bugs in here.
查理的鼻子比人类要灵敏四十四倍
Charlie's nose is 44 times more sensitive than ours.
他可以直接嗅出臭虫的藏匿之处
He can literally sniff out the bedbugs.
寻
Seek.
如果找到了  他就会坐下来
If they are present, he's trained to sit down.
干得好  查理
Good boy, Charlie.
亚当只需知道臭虫的位置
It's all Adam needs to know.
臭虫现在有日益增加的趋势
Bedbugs are on the increase,
它们搭人类旅行的顺风车辗转迁移
hitchhiking as we travel from city to city,
主要出没于家具之中  比如卡萝尔家的沙发
often infesting furniture like Carol's sofa.
我极其痛恨它们
I do resent them,
但又敬畏有加
but I quite admire them as well.
它们确实非常神奇
They're actually quite amazing,
甚至令人毛骨悚然
which makes it even creepier, you know,
因为这就是我要奋起反抗的东西
because... that's what I'm up against.
不过有了亚当的喷剂和查理灵敏的鼻子
But with Adam's spray and Charlie's nose,
这些虫子终于棋逢对手了
the bugs here have met their match.
它毕竟是个都市入侵者
This is one urban intruder
没人愿意和它同床共枕
nobody wants to live with.
不过在世界的某些角落
In some parts of the world,
人们已经学会了
people have learned
令这些都市入侵者物尽其用
to put their urban invaders to good use.
摩洛哥小城非斯  和迪拜相似
The Moroccan city of Fez, a bit like Dubai,
也遇到鸽子的问题
has a problem with pigeons.
但与迪拜人驱赶它们的做法不同
But rather than chasing them away,
非斯人反而将其请进来
the people of Fez invite them in.
诺丁在自家屋顶上为鸽子安了家
Nordine has built a home for pigeons on his roof.
这间阁楼是专供野生鸽子住的
我为它们提供了各式各样的提篮做巢
它们在这里生活得很舒适
否则也不会去而复返
他这样做不仅是出于对动物的热爱
He doesn't do this just for the love of animals.
鸽子粪对于当地的一项工业至关重要
Pigeon droppings are vital to a local industry.
诺丁的朋友塔米就时常购买这些粪便
And Nordine's friend Tami has come to buy some.
我给你准备了一些
看看
这些溶在水里肯定非常好
真不错
就这些了吗
对  都在这里了
塔米在当地一家皮革厂工作
Tami works at the local tannery.
非斯是摩洛哥皮革工业的中心
Fez is the centre of the Moroccan leather industry.
这里生产的皮革因质地柔软而出名
The leather here is famed for its softness,
鸽子粪便就是这秘方之一
and the pigeon droppings are a secret ingredient.
这是加工过程中最重要的一步
野生鸽子粪
Wild pigeon droppings
含有一种特殊的酶  可以分解
contain an enzyme which eats at the protein
动物毛皮中的蛋白质  起到软化作用
in the animal skin, softening it up.
皮革要在大缸里浸泡三天
The hides are soaked in the vats for three days,
塔米要用脚来完成工作
and Tami works them with his feet.
这可能是世界上最臭气熏天的工作了
This could be the stinkiest job in the world.
我第一次往里倒鸽子粪时
开始味道还不重
可是过一会儿就非常难闻了
对于塔米而言  这工作的薪水还不错
For Tami, it's a price worth paying.
鸽子的排泄物可以大大软化皮料
The pigeon droppings give the skins a softness
这是任何人造化学品都比不上的
no man-made chemical can produce.
如果我们不加粪便
皮料就达不到上乘的品质
有了非斯野生鸽子的帮助
Thanks to Fez's wild pigeons,
这些皮革能卖到一个好价钱
the skins will reach the highest possible price.
另外一座风格迥异的城市
Another very different city
也和都市入侵者共同合作
is also working with an urban intruder.
有时  即使是最不受欢迎的物种
Sometimes even the most unlikely species
也能与人类化敌为友
can turn out to be good news.
得克萨斯州的奥斯汀市
Austin, Texas,
现在是一百五十万只无尾蝙蝠的家园
is now home to 1.5 million free-tail bats and,
它们在这里很受欢迎
today, they are very welcome here.
二十年前  当它们在奥斯汀市中心的
20 years ago they set up home
这座桥上安家落户时
on this bridge in downtown Austin,
居民们曾一度想把它们赶走
and the residents wanted to get rid of them.
迈克船长至今还记忆犹新
River boatman Captain Mike remembers it well.
它们已经飞起来了
They're already taking off.
看右手边那些大树顶上
Look over the tree tops along the right-hand side.
它们已经开始外出活动了
They are off and running.
的确有很多人
There was a fair amount of
非常害怕这些蝙蝠
people that were actually afraid of the bats
因为担心
because they were afraid
会被传染上狂犬病
we were going to have a rabies problem
或者爆发其他的疾病
or a disease outbreak,
所以当时有不少组织
so there were actually groups of people
游说议员和商界领袖
lobbying the city council and business leaders to
希望能将这些蝙蝠赶尽杀绝
figure out a way to exterminate the colony.
但是蝙蝠对这座城市却做出了卓越的贡献
But bats turned out to be helpful for the city.
通宵达旦的都市生活
The 24-hour urban lifestyle
意味着奥斯汀是一座不夜城
means that Austin is a city of light,
这引来了成千上万的昆虫
and that attracts millions of insects,
而它们恰是蝙蝠的美味便当
which are, in turn, fast food for bats.
每天晚上蝙蝠能吃掉六吨昆虫
Every night, the bats eat six tonnes of insects.
一年就能吃掉两千吨
That's an incredible 2,000 tonnes a year.
它们不仅仅是飞虫杀手
However, they're more than just bug-killers.
迈克船长更是从中嗅到了商机
Captain Mike saw bats as a commercial opportunity.
蝙蝠搬来这里后
I started doing bat-watching
我开始做蝙蝠观光的游船路线
cruises shortly after they moved in here,
一传十  十传百
and word spread and they started getting
观光路线越来越火
more and more popular.
在旺季  三月到十月期间
So we do those seven nights a
一周七天每晚都有观光游览
week during the season, from March to October.
蝙蝠对我的生意很是照顾
Bats have really helped me in my business,
我爱它们
so I love them.
如果你往桥底下看
If you look up underneath the bridge,
能看到蝙蝠从那些裂缝中飞出来
you will watch them drop out of these cracks here.
由于游客来观赏蝙蝠
Visitors who come to see the bats
这里的旅游业每年有一千万美元的收入
generate $10 million in tourist revenue every year.
因此这种无尾蝙蝠在德州属于保护动物
So the free-tail bats of the state capital are now protected.
看来人类仍然期望回归自然
It turns out we still want to be connected to nature,
也许这是我们一直以来的夙愿
and perhaps we always have.
在印度  一些居民
In India, one group of people
将对动物的保护行为发挥到了极致
take caring for animals to the ultimate extreme,
而且他们世世代代皆是如此
and they've been doing it for centuries.
希亚姆・桑德在他的家乡拉贾斯坦的近郊
Shyam Sunder has rescued a chinkara gazelle
救了一只瞪羚
on the outskirts of his town in Rajasthan.
她的妈妈被杀死了
Her mother has been killed.
小瞪羚若不喝奶便无法存活
Without milk, the fawn will not survive,
因此希亚姆将它带回了家
so Shyam is taking her home.
在我们这里
大家都很喜爱小瞪羚
看我给妈妈带来什么了
一旦小瞪羚
来到我们的居所
便马上成为家庭中的一员
他们给她起名为阿缇
They're calling her Arti,
并在她额头点上檀香以示欢迎
and a spot of sandalwood honours her arrival.
欢迎你  阿缇
希亚姆的妻子凯安曾照顾过很多瞪羚
Kyran, Shyam's wife, has cared for many gazelles.
上次我照顾的小瞪羚是个孤儿
它的妈妈被狗咬死了
桑德一家人信奉印度教
The Sunders belong to a Hindu
崇尚自然之神  比什诺伊
sect of nature worshippers called the Bishnoi.
希亚姆为比什诺伊神庙供应牛奶
Shyam supplies milk to the Bishnoi temple,
那里收留了很多孤儿
which has its own orphans to care for.
比什诺伊是印度最早的环保主义者
The Bishnoi were India's first environmentalists
他们将自己的传统
and have brought their traditions
带到每个角落
from the country into the towns and cities.
他们将瞪羚视为自己的孩子
It is their belief that gazelles are their children
源于这种信奉  比什诺伊的妇女
and so the Bishnoi women
对它们百般呵护
show an incredible act of kindness.
她们亲自哺乳那些不愿喝瓶装奶的小瞪羚
They breast-feed the fawns that don't take to the bottle.
可以吗
没关系
对瞪羚来讲  母乳喂养是最佳方式
Even for gazelles, breast is best.
我必须先保证它有奶喝
因为它不喝别的奶
在我们这里  这是司空见惯的事情
小瞪羚对我们来说是神圣的
在与新家庭相处六周之后  阿缇断奶了
After six weeks with her new family, Arti is weaned.
它现在结实又健康
She's now fit and healthy.
希亚姆可以带它回归自然了
Shyam can take her back to the wild.
每个母亲送别自己的孩子都十分伤感
Watching a child leave home is always tough for a mum,
即便这个母亲只是临时的
even a surrogate one.
阿缇回到沙漠了
Arti is returned to the desert,
它将与自己的群落一同生活
where she'll join up with the wild herds.
这只不过是一念之慈
This may appear to be a tiny gesture of kindness,
但我们这些都市居民需要依赖于
but all of us who live in cities need the nature that exists
城市堡垒之外的自然环境
beyond the city walls,
因为大自然为都市各类需求提供资源
because the natural world feeds our hungry cities.
都市丛林得到了其所需的一切
And what the urban jungle needs, the urban jungle gets.
目前  城市人口数量已突破三十亿
More than three billion of us now live in cities.
为保证如此庞大人口的正常生活
To feed this huge population,
我们一年到头都在不停地
we ship in billions of
运输大量新鲜食品和农产品
tons of fresh food and produce all year round.
科技发展已允许我们从千里之外
We have the technology to bring in what we want
运输各类所需物品
from thousands of kilometres away.
在西班牙本地可以种植桃子
Peaches may grow here in Spain,
但却从南美洲进口
but these are imported from South America.
我们可以随时得到自己所需要的物品
We consume what we want, when we want it.
饮食已不再受地理和季节的束缚
We no longer need to eat locally or seasonally.
然而我们的胃口永难满足
And we have an insatiable appetite.
虽然娴熟于从自然界中获取
We've never been so good at exploiting nature.
但却难以处理其带来的后果
But we're not quite so good at dealing with the consequences.
巨大的消耗产生了大量的垃圾
Massive consumption creates mountains of waste.
仅在英国  每年就能产生
In the UK alone, we produce
一亿吨的垃圾
over 100 million tons of rubbish each year.
我们将之倾倒在杳无人烟的郊外
And we dump it safely out of sight.
内衣物品
而在某些地区  垃圾堆成了少数人的家园
But in some places, this world is home to an unfortunate few.
二十四小时购物
这里是肯尼亚的蒙巴萨
Here in Mombasa, Kenya,
人们赖以生存的正是他人丢弃的垃圾
people must scratch a living from the things others throw away.
对于阿什和她的家人来说
For Ashe and her family,
这个垃圾场既是家也是百宝箱
this dump is both home and hunting ground.
他们是现代社会的采猎者
They are modern-day hunter-gatherers,
在都市丛林的阴暗角落里
adapted to survival on the dark side
挣扎求生
of the urban jungle.
大多时候  一觉醒来
我就会来到这个垃圾场开始寻觅
在这里其实就是拾破烂
比如说瓶子  罐头
麻袋  还有塑料制品
捡得差不多之后
就拿去卖
垃圾车里也有食物
有扁豆  玉米和大豆之类的
垃圾车到达以后
When a rubbish truck arrives,
一场争夺大战就开始了
the race is on to grab the best scraps.
阿什的丈夫阿里正身处其中
Ashe's husband, Ali, gets stuck in.
这便是边缘生活
This really is life on the edge,
在城市垃圾中为自己的孩子寻找食物
finding food for your children in a city's rubbish.
目前  大多数人类都居住在城市里
More than half of us now live in cities.
我们正以空前的速度消耗着自然资源
And we're using up nature's resources as never before.
毫无疑问  我们是这个星球上最具创造力
We are, without doubt, the most inventive
且最强大的生物
and powerful creature on the planet.
我们是如此成功
We're so successful,
为满足自己的需求  搜刮了星球的每个角落
we've hijacked the whole world for our own ends.
然而  这种贪欲带来的后果
But the consequences of our
已经无法控制
voracious lives are spiralling out of control.
我们已经让自然界陷入危机了吗
Are we pushing the natural world towards a crisis?
我们该怎么办
Where do we go from here?
现在已经出现了一部分引领时代的先驱者
There are a few people who seem to be heading in a new direction.
他们正在尝试建造一座与自然协调的城市
One challenge is to design a city that's in balance with nature.
这是马斯达  一个位于
This is Masdar, a green
阿布扎比沙漠的绿色之城
city being built in the desert of Abu Dhabi.
这座城市的设计者是建筑师诺曼・福斯特
It's designed by architect Norman Foster.
马斯达令我很振奋
Masdar excites me
因为这是目前
because it's really the only true experiment
地球上唯一一座
on the planet, at the moment,
旨在达到零碳无污染的
in terms of seeking to achieve an environment,
社区  或者说是小型城市的实验基地
a community, a mini city, which is carbon free and waste free.
建在世界任何地方都会是个严峻的挑战
Now, that would be a tough challenge anywhere in the world.
要想在沙漠里完成这样的工程  别人会说
To do it in a desert environment, you could say, you know,
"这想法都很疯狂"
''You must be crazy to even attempt it.''
马斯达将以太阳能作为能源
Masdar will be powered by the sun.
在这里不会浪费一滴水
It will not waste a single drop of water.
没有消耗汽油的汽车
There will be no need for gas-guzzling cars.
建造马斯达的出发点
The starting point for Masdar
是与自然协作  根据太阳活动周期
was really working with nature, in terms of the solar cycle,
种植树木  并不仅仅为了美观
making the greenery, not just a cosmetic greenery,
而是营造绿荫  消耗我们所产生的废物
but creating shade, burning the waste that we produce
并在这个过程中制造能源
and, out of that process, creating energy.
这个工程源于自然  利用科技
So it's starting with nature and then it's using the technology,
与自然鼎力合作  相辅相成
working with nature, in harness with nature.
这项宏图大志定能取得成功
It is a noble ambition and it can be achieved.
然而  当前最紧要的
However, the immediate challenge
是想办法改变
is to try and change the way
城市里  我们与自然共存的方式
we live with nature in our existing cities.
这里是纽约联合广场的市场
This is the Union Square market in New York.
田间种植  西红柿
这里卖的商品都产自本地  通常生长在
It sells produce that's grown locally, often on the rooftops
纽约大楼的天台上
of New York's tower blocks.
你好  想尝尝我们的蜂蜜吗
Hello, would you like to try some of our honey?
荞麦粉
Buckwheat.
本地人吗  浓缩蜂蜜要吗  女士
Local? Whipped honey, Miss?
-不要吗  -怕甜吗
- No? - Too sweet?
不喜欢甜吗
You're sweet enough?
早上好
Good morning.
要蜂蜜吗  小姐  来就对了
Honey for you, Miss? Ah, you're doing the right thing.
传统主义者
A traditionalist.
安德鲁・科特是
Andrew Cote is the guru
高级养蜂专家  传到他已是第三代
of high-rise beekeeping and a third generation beekeeper.
直到最近  在纽约城里养蜂
Until recently, urban beekeeping
还是非法的  但这并不能阻止安德鲁
was illegal in New York, but that didn't stop Andrew.
我从没被抓住过
Personally, in my case, I was never caught.
虽然我养蜂的事情众所周知
Even though I was very public about having bees,
但我从未透漏过养蜂地点
I didn't tell people exactly where they were.
先生  十美元  来一罐吗
Yes, sir. $10, would you like a bag?
好消息是  纽约把这条禁令取消了
Happily, New York changed its mind and Andrew's mission
于是安德鲁开始将蜜蜂普及到各家各户
is to bring bees into everyone's lives.
今天  他来到曼哈顿一座豪华公寓的阳台
Today, he's on the balcony of a swanky Manhattan apartment
同他一起的是新手王薇薇
with novice, Vivien Wang.
你可能会对蜂箱的盖子望而却步
You're going to have a problem with the outer cover,
因为蜜蜂太多了
because there are a lot of bees on the inside of it.
喷烟
Smoke 'em.
只要看见蜜蜂就喷烟
Smoke 'em if you got 'em.
安德鲁有点像是蜂王
Andrew is sort of the king bee,
在城市养蜂业里
I think, of urban beekeeping,
作为他的学生
and those of us who are his students,
我觉得自己就像是蜂蜜大师的学徒
I think of myself as the honey sorcerer's apprentice, in a way.
你看到什么了
What do you see?
这下面覆盖着很多蜂蜜
I see a lot of cap honey under here.
这东西有点像
And I see... it looks like...
花蜜
a lot of nectar.
对这位纽约的律师来说  这是个新奇的经历
It's an unusual pastime for a New York lawyer.
当我告诉我的朋友
I think my friends, when I told them
我要开始学习养蜂
that I was going to start being a beekeeper,
他们都很震惊  他们觉得这事既古怪又奇妙
were amused. They thought it was quirky but kind of wonderful,
因为这是与大自然接触的与众不同的方式
because it's a different way for us to all connect with nature.
我想我们都需要在生活中加点料
I think all of us need a little more sweetness in our lives
这令我们的视野投放于
and it's nice to be able to cast our eyes
城市上空  远离嘈杂
skyward in this city, you know, away and above the traffic,
脑子里只想着周围嗡嗡乱窜的蜜蜂
and think about all these bees buzzing above our heads.
但作为养蜂新手  意外总是难免的
But being a novice beekeeper has its ups and downs.
怎么了
What, what, what?
没事  我没想到
Nothing. Sorry, I didn't know
它们能蛰到我的手
they could sting through hands quite like that.
它们在疯狂地蜇人  你先离开这儿
They're stinging me like crazy. I really want you to let go.
目前有一千万只蜜蜂
There are now nearly ten
生活在纽约的屋顶上
million bees living on the rooftops of New York.
在皇后区的河边
Over the river in Queens,
今天是养蜂人史芬尼的好日子
it's a special day for beekeeper Stefanos.
他正在安德鲁的协助下收获第一桶蜂蜜
He's harvesting his first honey with Andrew's help.
-这个很棒  没法再好了  -是啊  看
- This one's perfect. Couldn't be better. - Oh, yes, look.
我觉得我们该尝尝味道
I think we should give the honey a taste, just...
以求确保
Just to make sure.
伙计  这绝对是极品
Oh, man, this is going to be so good.
我的天
Oh, my God.
这味道就像是阳光味的焦糖
It's like caramelised sunlight.
-你在做质检  -没错
- It's just quality control. - Right.
蜜蜂酿蜜  还能对公园和花园里的花朵授粉
Bees make honey and they pollinate the city's parks and gardens.
但最重要的是
But most importantly,
它们令纽约人回到了大自然的怀抱
they bring New Yorkers back in touch with nature.
我觉得城市里很多人都在养蜂
I think a lot of people are beekeeping in the city
因为他们想更亲近大自然
because they want to feel a connection to nature.
他们住在高楼大厦  走在沥青马路
They live in tall buildings, they walk on asphalt,
平时乘坐地铁
they ride around in trains under the ground.
如果在楼顶有这么个蜂箱
When they have a beehive on their roof,
他们每周就能花上一两个小时
they can spend one or two hours a week,
真正去亲近大自然  自食其力
and really be connected to nature, and be creating their own food
没有碳足迹  我觉得这很棒
with almost no footprint, and I think that's great.
纽约的养蜂业虽不能拯救地球
Beekeeping in New York isn't going to save the planet,
但至少前进了一大步
but it's a step in the right direction.
毫无疑问
There is just no doubt.
如若我们继续居住在城市
If we are to continue living in cities,
就必须停止向大自然的肆意掠夺
we'll have to stop stripping
静心想想人类的未来
nature bare with no thought for tomorrow.
我们在室内和户外的所作所为
What we do in our homes
将会影响到整个地球
and in our streets affects the entire planet.
人类文明的未来
The future of our civilisation
取决于我们重建
depends on us restoring the balance
大自然与都市丛林间的平衡关系
between the natural world and the urban jungle.
我们能做到吗
Can we do it?
希望的曙光在世界各地熠熠发光
There are clear signs of hope from around the world.
我们的聪明才智和创造力
We do have the intelligence and ingenuity
能够适应变幻莫测的世界
to adapt to a changing world.
古老的训鹰术
The ancient art of falconry
现在用来保护迪拜这座现代都市
now helps protect the modern city of Dubai.
我们能够与大自然联手
We can work hand in hand
解决我们所面临的问题
with nature to solve the problems we face.
在印度  我们用无花果树建造的桥仍在生长
In India, we train fig trees to make living bridges.
我们与大象合作获取珍贵的木材
And we team up with elephants to extract valuable timber
却不毁坏整个森林
without trashing the whole forest.
我们可以站在整体的角度思考问题
We can think as a community
未雨绸缪
and plan ahead.
在马里
In Mali,
每年人们只能在这片湖里捕一次鱼
the fish in this lake are shared out only once a year.
当人类与自然合作  就能取得卓越成就
When we work together, it's incredible what we can achieve.
泥泞的杰内古城的居民
Everyone in the mud city of Djenne
通力协作保护他们神圣的清真寺
collaborates to protect their sacred mosque.
面对逆境  我们拥有如此斗志和胆识
We have such spirit and such bravery in the face of adversity.
如果我们能将这种本能
If we combine these natural abilities
与完美的想象力和高明的见解相结合
with the best of our imagination and our biggest ideas,
那我们的城市定能续写新的篇章
then surely our cities can adapt and change.
人类星球的命运就掌握在我们手中
The destiny of our planet is now in human hands.
人类星球
镜头背后的故事
《人类星球》摄制组历时三年
Over three years, the Human Planet team
前往世界各地对人物进行拍摄
has filmed people around the world.
这些人都有着惊人的忍耐力
All had amazing endurance,
各自的生存秘诀和聪明才智
local know-how, and ingenuity.
仅是跟拍就是一个巨大的挑战
Just keeping up with them proved to be a huge challenge.
摄制组的要求和装备
The demands on our teams and kit
迫使他们挑战极限
pushed them to the limit.
拍摄爪哇岛的活火山
Filming on an active volcano
测试了摄像机的极限工作能力
in Java tested the cameras to breaking point.
工作人员来此拍摄硫磺矿
The crew were here to film sulphur miners.
周围的空气对人体和器材都有损害
The air they breathe was a danger to both people and kit.
蒂娜・穆芙蒂
人类星球剧组调研员
我要走近一点  用气量计
I'm just going to go in there, a bit closer, with a gas meter
测试一下环境
and see what it does.
读数为百万分之九十三
It's reading 93 parts per million.
现在升到一百九十四了
It's going up to 194 now.
我们在烟雾的正中心  得赶快离开这里
So we're right in the middle of a cloud. We've got to get out.
这是安全工作上限的四十倍
This is 40 times the safe working limit.
这种气体是一种硫化氢的混合物
The gas is a hydrogen sulphide mix
其所到之处  必受腐蚀
that corrodes every surface it lands on.
防毒面具保护了工作人员
The gas masks protected the crew,
而摄像机却遭了殃
but not the cameras.
摄像机出现电磁射频的警告
We've got an RF warning on the camera,
基斯・帕特里奇
摄像师
就是说信号没法传入录像带
which means that the signal's not actually getting onto the tape.
一般是磁头堵塞
It's usually a head clog.
工作人员发现硫化物的微粒粘在了磁头上
The crew found that sulphide particles had stuck to the tape head
现在必须拆机
and open-heart surgery was needed.
这真是太脏了
That's absolutely filthy.
清理之后  摄像机又能重新工作了
After cleaning, the camera lived to work another day.
然而这些问题
But the crew's problems
和那些每天面对硫磺矿的矿工相比
were nothing compared to those faced daily
简直不值一提
by the sulphur miners.
在婆罗洲附近的苏禄海中
In the Sulu Sea off Borneo,
摄像师西蒙・恩德比
cameraman Simon Enderby
拍下了渔民萨尔兵惊人的屏气潜水过程
filmed a remarkable free-diving fisherman called Sulbin.
现在我配置着最先进的水中呼吸器
Here I was with the latest in scuba gear,
而他只穿着泳裤  戴着木质游泳镜
and he was swimming in a pair of underpants and wooden goggles.
我们组成了极不协调的潜水二人组
We really made for a bizarre dive duo.
为了捕捉到完美的捕猎画面
To capture the perfect hunt,
身着潜水装置的我必须
I had to match my scuba-dive skills
配合好他的自由潜水
with those of Sulbin's free-diving.
保持相同的浮力  泳姿  找寻猎物
Our buoyancy, our swimming, our search for food, and, finally,
最后他成功捕获到一条鱼
his successful capture of a fish,
这些全部都要配合得天衣无缝
all had to evolve together.
幸运的是  在第三次潜水时
Luckily, on the third dive,
终于天时地利人和  我们都很满意
it all came together, and we both came up happy.
伙计  这次很好  这次太完美了
Oh, wow, mate, that's the one. That's definitely the one.
在菲律宾  我们拍摄渔民们
In the Philippines, we filmed fishermen
用一张大网捕捉暗礁里的鱼群
herding all the fish on a reef into a huge net.
在这  我们发现鱼的适应能力也很强
Here, we found that fish can be adaptable too.
摄影师罗杰・沐恩斯
Cameraman Roger Munns
无意间把一条鱼从餐桌上救了下来
inadvertently saved one fish from becoming supper.
他给它起名叫尼莫
He nicknamed him Nemo.
尼莫躲在罗杰的潜水装备里
Nemo sheltered in Roger's dive kit
直到危险解除
and hid there until the coast was clear,
才游回家园
eventually swimming off back home.
在我们拍摄的很多地方
We filmed in many locations
当地人甚至不知道摄像机为何物
where people had never seen film cameras before.
在印度北部  孩子们目不转睛地盯着镜头
In northern India, the children constantly looked into the lens.
为了拍到导演马克・福劳斯想要的镜头
So, to get the shots he wanted,
他试图用唱歌来转移孩子们的注意力
director Mark Flowers tried to distract the children by singing a song.
我这辈子从没唱过歌
I never sing in my whole life!
出乎他意料的是
Much to his surprise,
孩子们比他还熟悉这首儿歌的旋律
the children knew the nursery rhymes better than he did.
-一闪一闪亮晶晶  -我们学过
- Twinkle, twinkle, little star.  - We learn this.
满天都是小星星
How I wonder what you are.
挂在天上放光明  好像千万小眼睛
Up above the world so high. Like a diamond in the sky.
高空拍摄总会牵涉到复杂的安全措施
Filming at height always involves complex safety measures.
但在非洲中部  摄制小组的难度加大了
But in Central Africa, the crew had an added complication.
蒂姆・福格系上绳索拍摄泰特
Tim Fogg rigged ropes to film Tete collecting honey
在野生蜂巢取蜂蜜的场景
from a wild bees'nest.
不幸的是  愤怒的蜜蜂直冲蒂姆而来
Unfortunately, the angry bees went straight for Tim.
-他没事吧  -喷烟  喷烟  快点儿
- Think he'll be OK? - Smoke! Smoke! Smoke, quickly!
需要帮忙吗  蒂姆
Can we get you out, Tim?
我记得一开始
The first thing I remember
看见一只蜜蜂就在我的面前
seeing was a bee right in front of my face
腹部扭动  好像是要蛰我了
with its abdomen twisted as if it was ready to sting me.
它们进去了吗
They got inside?
没有  它们隔着面具
No, they were stinging
和手套叮咬
through the face mask and through the gloves.
在被蛰了三十个伤口后
After 30 stings,
蒂姆彻底折服于泰特
Tim fully appreciated Tete's
为家人寻找蜂蜜的勇气
bravery in gathering honey for his family.
拍摄人与动物时  一切都是未知的
When filming people with animals, nothing's entirely predictable.
在格陵兰岛  导演尼克・布朗想拍摄
In Greenland, director Nic Brown wanted to film
因纽特人捕捉睡鲨的场景
the Inuit catching the elusive Greenland shark
这种鲨鱼生活在深水区并难以捕捉
that lives in these deep waters.
在焦急地等待了十天后
After an anxious ten days,
每个人都很紧张
everyone was thrilled when,
终于在午夜
in the middle of the night,
他们感觉到有东西碰到绳子了
they finally felt something on the line.
西蒙・福斯特
录音师
我们都很兴奋
We're very excited
因为我们一直在玩弄这根绳子
because we've all been playing with the line
它深入水中八百米
that's 800 metres down into the water
而且你能明显感觉到鲨鱼就在绳子的那头
and you can actually feel the shark on the end of it.
我们觉得冰层下的某处
Somewhere down there we think we've got a,
睡鲨上钩了
er, Greenland shark on a hook.
我们非常期待
We're hoping.
这个洞是留给水下摄像机的
This is the hole for our underwater camera,
-而这个洞  -用来捕鲨的吗
- and this is the hole... - A shark hole?
对
for the shark.
他们发现低估了洞的大小
They discovered they'd underestimated the hole size,
因为简森斯捕到了一条四米长的鲨鱼
because the Jensens had caught a huge four-metre-long shark.
这洞口太小了
对  我们必须把洞凿宽点
直升机与地面活动的良好协调
Co-ordinating helicopters with action on the ground
既费钱又非易事
is both expensive and difficult.
在澳大利亚  导演苏珊・麦克米伦
But in Australia, director Susan McMillan
需要同时指挥三架直升机
had to co-ordinate three helicopters at once.
其中两架是由直升机驾驶员本・泰普
Two of them were flown by heli-cowboys Ben Tapp
和他的同伴兰金所驾驶
and his mate Rankin,
他们疯狂地驱赶牛群
dicing with death to corral their cattle.
空中三架直升机参与拍摄
The challenges of filming with three helicopters in the air
在这次行程中起到重要作用
have been quite considerable on this trip,
苏珊・麦克米伦
人类星球导演
因为这样的效果非常真实
because I'm filming it for real.
这不是拍戏  没有第二遍
It's not a drama and there's no take two.
我必须在事情发生的一瞬间捕获到镜头
I have to actually capture the event as it happens,
而且当时情况十分危险
and it's quite a dangerous situation.
天上有三架直升机
I've got three helicopters in the air,
地上有沙滩车和马
I've got quad bikes and horses on the ground,
还有狂奔的牛群
I've got stampeding cattle,
所以  最大的问题  就是保证安全
so, actually, the biggest pressure, I think, has been safety.
在地面的工作是相当危险的
Working on the ground can be just as dangerous,
尤其是遇见大型猫科动物时
especially when it comes to big cats.
摄制组想拍摄肯尼亚的多罗博人
The crew wanted to film Dorobo tribesmen in Kenya
追杀狮子的镜头
chasing lions off a kill.
摄影师托比・斯特朗主动请缨跟拍
So cameraman Toby Strong offered to film with them on foot,
以便拍摄他们行动最为激烈的时刻
to be in the thick of the action.
不用汽车
The thought of getting out
徒步走向狮子这个想法
of a vehicle and walking towards lions on foot
与我整个人都格格不入
goes against every common sense bone in my body.
我是说  这些人  太强悍了
I mean, these guys are... these guys are amazing.
他们拿着弓箭
They, um... They've got their bows and arrows.
但我什么都没有
But, um, I haven't got anything!
我只有...
I've got...
我只有摄像机和镜头盖来保护自己
...I've got a camera and a lens cap to protect myself with.
有点动真格了  对吧
It's getting a bit real, though, isn't it?
真令人忐忑
Butterflies in the stomach.
确定狮子的方位后
Having located the lions,
托比跟随多罗博人一起前进
Toby followed the Dorobo as they moved in
去看个究竟
to have a look.
朝茂密的灌木丛走去
Walking down there towards thick
而且你明明还知道那里有狮子
bushes where you know there are lions,
天呐  脖颈发凉
God, it's something very primal in the back of your neck,
毛骨悚然
and everything... the hairs on the back of your neck
感觉自己万众瞩目
and you just feel these eyes on you,
但是非常有活力
but you feel very, very alive.
真是神奇的感觉
It's a magical feeling.
我似乎对所有人都说了
It's, um... I sort of recommend it to everyone.
工作之前  在狮城散散步
Before going to work, have a walk through lion country.
这会加强自己的理解能力
It gets things in perspective.
真的  很神奇
Yeah, amazing.
若没有世界各地所拍之人的
Without the co-operation and support of all the people
配合与支持
we filmed around the world,
就不可能有本片的诞生
this series could not have been made.
他们独特的知识与生存技能
Their unique knowledge and survival skills
在人口渐增的地球之上
have relevance for us all
起着举足轻重的作用
in an increasingly human planet.
第八集  完  [本片终]